<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Pharmacy</title>
	<atom:link href="https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy</link>
	<description>Online Medicine Pharmacy</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 10:40:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Bempedoic Acid Clinical Pearls</title>
		<link>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/bempedoic-acid-clinical-pearls/</link>
					<comments>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/bempedoic-acid-clinical-pearls/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[project7272]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 10:39:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Pharmacy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/?p=184</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Bempedoic acid, also known as Nexletol, is a once-daily medication used in patients with increased atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (ASCVD) or...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Bempedoic acid, also known as Nexletol, is a once-daily medication used in patients with increased atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (ASCVD) or heterozygous familial hypercholesterolemia who are requiring additional LDL-C lowering previously on a maximally tolerated statin therapy along with maintaining a healthy diet. In this article, we will further break down some of the most important bempedoic acid clinical pearls.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Dosing of Bempedoic Acid</h2>



<p>What is the dosing for bempedoic acid? Bempedoic is a once-daily medication that doesn’t need to be titrated. Standard dosing is 180mg once daily which can be taken with or without food.&nbsp; There is no dose adjustment needed in patients with mild or moderate renal impairment, however, there is limited data available in patients with severe renal impairment which is classified as having an eGFR&lt;30mL/min/1.73m2. If a patient presents with hepatic insufficiencies, there is no dose adjustment needed, although patients with severe hepatic impairment, defined as Child-Pugh C, have not been studied.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Bempedoic Acid Clinical Pearls and Adverse Effects</h2>



<p>What are the most common side effects? One of the most notable adverse effects is hyperuricemia. This is usually seen within the first 4 weeks of being on the medication but could happen throughout the treatment. These high levels of uric acid could lead to symptoms like warm tender joints, swelling, and may even lead to gout. Other noted side effects include back and stomach pain, muscle spasms, pain in the shoulder, legs, or arms, bronchitis, and anemia. Tendon problems can happen as well, especially in patients who are greater than 60 years old, on fluoroquinolones, have renal failure, or are taking corticosteroids. There is no data available that shows Bempedoic acid is safe in pregnancy. Risk vs. benefit should be discussed before using in this population.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Drug Interactions</h2>



<p>Are there any drug interactions? If Bempedoic acid is taken along with Simvastatin, it is recommended to avoid doses greater than 20mg. This is partly because Bempedoic Acid 180mg along with 40mg of Simvastatin was found to increase Simvastatin AUC by 2-fold. The mechanism of this interaction has yet to be reported. Bempedoic acid or any of its active metabolites are not metabolized or interact with any cytochrome P450 enzymes. Pravastatin doses greater than 40mg are to be avoided as well due to an increased risk of myopathy. Atorvastatin and Rosuvastatin didn’t have any maximum dose considerations.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Where Might You See It?</h2>



<p>What patients could benefit from this medication? This medication could be used as an adjunct in patients who eat a healthy diet and can’t tolerate a max dose statin whose LDL-C is not at goal. Bempedoic acid is a prodrug that gets converted into the active moiety, ACSVL1 which is not present in muscles.&nbsp; This medication gives patients a more affordable option compared to injectable PCSK9 medications although the LDL lowering effect is less (15-20% range). Representatives from the company have eyed a price range of around $10 a pill or $3,650 per year. Compared to PCSK9 injectables like Repatha, which costs patients around $6,000 per year. This would save the patient around 65% per year.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In addition, this agent is oral, so in patients who will not accept an injection (i.e. PCSK9 medications), we have another option besides ezetimibe in cholesterol management.</p>



<p>This article (Bempedoic Acid Clinical Pearls) was written by Cody Springer, PharmD Candidate in collaboration with Eric Christianson, PharmD, BCPS, BCGP</p>



<p><a href="https://www.meded101.com/free-webinar/">Did you enjoy this blog post? Subscribers are emailed when new blog posts. In addition, you’ll get access to the free giveaways below. Over 6,000 healthcare professionals have subscribed for our FREE Giveaways. Why haven’t you?!</a></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.meded101.com/free-webinar/">30 medication mistakes PDF</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.meded101.com/free-webinar/">18+ Page Drug Interaction PDF</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.meded101.com/free-webinar/">10 Commandments of Polypharmacy Webinar based on my experiences in clinical practice</a></li>
</ul>



<p>References:</p>



<ul>
<li>“Pam R. Taub, MD, on a New Approach for Managing Lipids.”&nbsp;<em>Consultant360</em>, www.consultant360.com/exclusive/cardiology/lipid-metabolic/5-questions-about-new-approach-managing-lipids.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Nadeem, Dania, and Trisha Roy. “Esperion Says Cholesterol Drug Gets U.S. Approval; Eyes $10 per Pill Pricing.”&nbsp;<em>Reuters</em>, Thomson Reuters, 21 Feb. 2020, www.reuters.com/article/us-esperion-thera-fda/u-s-fda-approves-esperions-cholesterol-drug-idUSKBN20F2NQ.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Nexeltol (Bempedoic acid) package insert:</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/bempedoic-acid-clinical-pearls/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bactrim CHF Case Study</title>
		<link>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/bactrim-chf-case-study/</link>
					<comments>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/bactrim-chf-case-study/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[project7272]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 10:37:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Pharmacy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/?p=181</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One thing I always encourage is critical thinking. Reviewing a diagnosis list will give you clues as to the likely...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>One thing I always encourage is critical thinking. Reviewing a diagnosis list will give you clues as to the likely medications that a patient is taking or should be taking if they are following guideline-based medication therapy. In this&nbsp;<a href="https://www.reallifepharmacology.com/sulfamethoxazole-and-trimethoprim-rlp-episode-026/">Bactrim</a>&nbsp;CHF case study, I review some of the important clinical pearls that may come up when you see Bactrim (sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim) used in a patient with CHF.</p>



<p>KE is a 77-year-old female who lives at an assisted living facility. Her caregivers have encouraged her to see a primary care provider due to increasing lethargy, mild confusion, and mild pain associated with urination. At her appointment, she was diagnosed with a urinary tract infection and prescribed Bactrim DS 1 tablet BID for 7 days, then reassess.</p>



<p>Her past medical history is complex and includes CHF and atrial fibrillation amongst other diagnoses. She is taking numerous medications which includes:</p>



<ul>
<li>Aspirin 81 mg daily</li>



<li>Entresto 97/103 mg BID</li>



<li>Toprol XL 25 mg QD</li>



<li>Spironolactone 50 mg QD</li>



<li>Empagliflozin 10 mg daily</li>



<li>Omeprazole 20 mg daily</li>



<li>Acetaminophen 500 mg PRN</li>



<li>Cyclobenzaprine 10 mg HS PRN back pain</li>



<li>Atorvastatin 80 mg daily</li>



<li>Lidoderm patch as needed</li>



<li>Sertraline 25 mg daily</li>



<li>Warfarin titrated to an INR of 2-3</li>
</ul>



<p>As a pharmacist, I’m always looking at the medication list to ensure we don’t run into drug interactions or unnecessary complications from new medications.</p>



<p>The first concern I have with Bactrim is the potential for it to cause hyperkalemia. This patient is on two medications that are commonly used for heart failure that can cause hyperkalemia. Both spironolactone and Entresto (contains valsartan) are going to raise the risk for hyperkalemia. At the very minimum, we need to ensure that potassium levels are monitored if the Bactrim prescription is going to be given to this patient. Here’s one of my&nbsp;<a href="https://www.meded101.com/trimethoprim-and-hyperkalemia/">all-time favorite donated cases demonstrating how high a potassium level can go due to this interaction!</a></p>



<p>Obviously, this patient likely has a history of HFrEF with the medications that are being prescribed. If Bactrim is prescribed to a heart failure patient, it is additionally important to ask about fluid restrictions. It is recommended to give Bactrim with 8 ounces of water to reduce the risk of crystalluria. This may be another reason why Bactrim is not advantageous.</p>



<p>In addition to the potential additive drug interaction with potassium-elevating medications, warfarin can also interact with Bactrim. This one recently made my&nbsp;<a href="https://www.meded101.com/top-10-drug-interactions-my-list/">Top 10 list!</a>&nbsp;Bactrim will likely raise the concentrations of warfarin leading to an elevated INR. We need to monitor the INR with this drug interaction. If Bactrim has to be used as the antibiotic of choice, most clinicians will assess INR within 3-5 days of starting the Bactrim. In rare instances, I have seen clinicians proactively reduce the dose of warfarin. It was unclear why this patient is not on apixaban or another DOAC but that remains a consideration to review.</p>



<p>The last issue of note is the UTI itself. Empagliflozin should at least be assessed to ensure that this drug is not contributing to the UTI problem. I’d want to know some past history here and see if recurrent UTIs have been happening and if so, we may have to consider alternative therapy.</p>



<p>Hopefully this Bactrim CHF case study reminds you to look at the diagnosis list in addition to the medications. It may help you identify patients who are at risk for drug interactions and other complications.</p>



<p>Eric Christianson, PharmD, BCPS, BCGP</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/bactrim-chf-case-study/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Comprehensive Guide to Lower Cholesterol and Reduce Heart Attack or Stroke Risk</title>
		<link>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/a-comprehensive-guide-to-lower-cholesterol-and-reduce-heart-attack-or-stroke-risk/</link>
					<comments>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/a-comprehensive-guide-to-lower-cholesterol-and-reduce-heart-attack-or-stroke-risk/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[project7272]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 10:29:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Pharmacy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/?p=177</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Introduction Understanding Cholesterol How Lipitor Works Benefits of Lipitor Potential Side Effects of Lipitor Precautions and Interactions Lifestyle Changes to...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Introduction</h2>



<ul>
<li>What is Lipitor (Atorvastatin)?</li>



<li>Why is Lipitor prescribed?</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Understanding Cholesterol</h2>



<ul>
<li>What is cholesterol?</li>



<li>Good cholesterol vs. bad cholesterol</li>



<li>The role of cholesterol in heart disease</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How Lipitor Works</h2>



<ul>
<li>Mechanism of action</li>



<li>How long does it take for Lipitor to work?</li>



<li>Lipitor dosage and administration</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Benefits of Lipitor</h2>



<ul>
<li>Lowering cholesterol levels</li>



<li>Reducing the risk of heart attack or stroke</li>



<li>Other benefits of Lipitor</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Potential Side Effects of Lipitor</h2>



<ul>
<li>Common side effects</li>



<li>Serious side effects</li>



<li>Who should not take Lipitor?</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Precautions and Interactions</h2>



<ul>
<li>Precautions to take while using Lipitor</li>



<li>Interactions with other drugs and supplements</li>



<li>Lipitor and alcohol consumption</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Lifestyle Changes to Complement Lipitor Use</h2>



<ul>
<li>Exercise</li>



<li>Healthy diet</li>



<li>Weight management</li>



<li>Smoking cessation</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Lipitor vs. Other Cholesterol-Lowering Drugs</h2>



<ul>
<li>How does Lipitor compare to other statins?</li>



<li>How does Lipitor compare to non-statin cholesterol-lowering drugs?</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Lipitor for Children and Pregnant Women</h2>



<ul>
<li>Is Lipitor safe for children?</li>



<li>Is Lipitor safe for pregnant women?</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Lipitor and the Future of Cholesterol Treatment</h2>



<ul>
<li>Ongoing research and development</li>



<li>Potential advancements in cholesterol treatment</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h2>



<ul>
<li>Summary of Lipitor&#8217;s benefits and potential side effects</li>



<li>Importance of talking to your healthcare provider before starting Lipitor</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">FAQs</h2>



<ol>
<li>How long does it take for Lipitor to start working?</li>



<li>Is it safe to take Lipitor while pregnant?</li>



<li>Can Lipitor cause muscle pain?</li>



<li>Can Lipitor be taken with other medications?</li>



<li>Is it possible to lower cholesterol without medication?</li>
</ol>



<p>Lipitor (Atorvastatin) is a widely prescribed medication used to lower cholesterol levels and reduce the risk of heart attack or stroke. In this article, we will cover the basics of cholesterol, how Lipitor works, its benefits, potential side effects, precautions to take, lifestyle changes to complement its use, and its comparison with other cholesterol-lowering drugs.</p>



<p>Cholesterol is a fat-like substance produced by the liver and found in some foods. High levels of bad cholesterol (LDL) can cause plaque buildup in the arteries, leading to heart disease. Lipitor works by blocking the enzyme that produces cholesterol in the liver, resulting in lower cholesterol levels in the blood.</p>



<p>Lipitor is usually prescribed as a daily dose, and it may take up to four weeks to see significant cholesterol reduction. However, some people may experience side effects such as muscle pain, nausea, and diarrhea. It&#8217;s essential to talk to your healthcare provider before starting Lipitor to determine if it&#8217;s the right medication for you.</p>



<p>Along with Lipitor, lifestyle changes such as exercising, eating a healthy diet, managing weight, and quitting smoking can significantly lower cholesterol levels and reduce the risk of heart disease.</p>



<p>While Lipitor is generally safe and effective, it&#8217;s not recommended for pregnant women, people with liver disease, or those who are allergic to atorvastatin. It&#8217;s also important to avoid drinking alcohol while taking Lipitor, as it can increase the risk of liver damage.</p>



<p>In conclusion, Lipitor (Atorvastatin) is a valuable medication for people with high cholesterol levels, and it can significantly reduce the risk of heart attack or stroke. However, it&#8217;s essential to discuss the potential benefits and risks with your healthcare provider before starting Lipitor.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://omayer1728.github.io/pharmacy/a-comprehensive-guide-to-lower-cholesterol-and-reduce-heart-attack-or-stroke-risk/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
